<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="samples">
  <title>Sample Applications</title>

  <para>The Spring GemFire project includes one sample application. Named
  "Hello World", the sample demonstrates how to configure and use GemFire
  inside a Spring application. At runtime, the sample offers a
  <emphasis>shell</emphasis> to the user for running various commands against
  the grid. It provides an excellent starting point for users unfamiliar with
  the essential components or the Spring and GemFire concepts.</para>

  <para>The sample is bundled with the distribution and is included in the
  main solution file. You can also run it from the command line once it is
  built in visual studio.</para>

  <section>
    <title>Prerequisites</title>

    <para>1. You will need to <ulink
    url="http://download.gemstone.com/">download</ulink>, install, and obtain
    a license for</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>GemFire Enterprise 6.0</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>GemFire Enterprise Native Client 3.0.0.9</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The GemFire Enterprise licence file, gemfireLicense.zip should
    reside in the root of your GemFire Enterprise install directory. The
    GemFire Enterprise Native Client licence file, gfCpplicense.zip, should
    reside in the 'bin' sub-directory of the Native Client install
    directory.</para>

    <para>The .NET clients run in a client-server architecture. This is shown
    below from the perspective of a single 'native (C++ or .NET) client and a
    single cache server process.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Client-Server Configuration for native (C++ or .NET)
      clients</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/cache-server.png" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>While not shown in this picture, there can be multiple .NET/C++
    client applications and also multiple other processes that act in a
    peer-to-peer like manner as part of the GemFire Distributed System.</para>

    <para>When running in a client-server architecture there needs to be
    configuration of the client side, the .NET/C++ Application, and the data
    grid side, the Java Cache Server. In this example the configuration of the
    client side is done entirely by the FactoryObject's declared in the Spring
    XML file. The data grid side is configured with a standalone configuration
    file.</para>

    <para>2. The Java Cache Server requires a configuration file in order to
    run. This file is provided in the Spring GemFire distribution and in named
    <literal>cache.xml</literal>. It is located in the
    'example\Spring.Data.Gemfire.HelloWorld' directory. It needs to be into
    the GemFire Enterprise 6.0 'bin' directory where the cacheserver.bat file
    is located.</para>

    <para>3. Run the cacheserver.bat file located in the 'bin' of the GemFire
    Enterprise 6.0 product. By default it will load a configuration file named
    '<literal>cache.xm</literal>l'.</para>

    <para>The Spring GemFire project ships with the essential GemFire client
    side libraries to run the sample application. Note that because the .NET
    Client API is a wrapper around the C++ API, it needs to be referenced in
    either the App.config file or installed into the GAC. The HelloWorld
    example program is configured to load the libraries from the
    'lib\GemFire\net\2.0' directory.</para>

    <para>Despite providing the client However, it is recommended that you
    download the GemFire Enterprise Native Client 3.0.0.9 from the download
    site to have access to reference documentation. You may also find the
    <ulink
    url="http://community.gemstone.com/display/gemfire/GemFire+.NET+API+Tour">GemFire
    .NET API Tour</ulink> of interest to read.</para>
  </section>

  <section id="samples:hello-world">
    <title>Hello World</title>

    <para>The Hello World sample demonstrates the basic functionality of the
    Spring GemFire project and is also useful to understand how GemFire
    clients work. The application bootstraps GemFire, configures it, allows
    for the execution of several commands against the data grid, and
    gracefully shuts down when the application exits. Multiple instances can
    be started at the same time as they will work with each other sharing data
    without any user intervention.</para>

    <section id="samples:hello-world:start-stop">
      <title>Compiling, starting and stopping
      the sample</title>

      <para>Hello World is designed as a stand-alone application. The main
      class is in the file <literal>Program.cs</literal> and generates an
      executable named <literal>HelloWorld.exe</literal>. To start the example
      follow the steps</para>

      <para>To compile the example, load the solution
      <literal>Spring.Data.GemFire.sln</literal> in the root of the Spring
      GemFire project directory.</para>

      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Load the Visual Studio 2008 solution Spring.Data.GemFire.sln
          located in the root of the Spring GemFire project directory. Compile
          the solution.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ensure that the Java Cache Server is running as described in
          the previous section.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Set the startup project to be the
          Spring.Data.Gemfire.HelloWorld project <emphasis
          role="bold">or</emphasis> cd to the
          '<literal>example\Spring.Data.Gemfire.HelloWorld\bin\Debug</literal>'
          directory and run <literal>HelloWorld.exe</literal>.<note>
              <para>You can pass as a command line argument the name that will
              appear before you enter commands in the shell. This is useful
              for distinguishing different members of the distributed
              system</para>
            </note></para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can now execute commands in the shell, which will be
          described in the next section. Exit the shell by typing
          '<literal>exit</literal>'.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>

    <section id="samples:hello-world:run">
      <title>Using the sample</title>

      <para>Once started, the sample will create a client side cache that is
      replicated with the server cache contained in the Java Cache Server. For
      example, the command line '<literal>HelloWorld.exe client-1</literal>'
      will result in the following greeting</para>

      <programlisting>Hello World!
Want to interact with the world ? ...
Supported commands are:

get &lt;key&gt; - retrieves an entry (by key) from the grid
put &lt;key&gt; &lt;value&gt; - puts a new entry into the grid
remove &lt;key&gt; - removes an entry (by key) from the grid
size - returns the size of the grid
clear - removes all mapping in the grid
keys - returns the keys contained by the grid
values - returns the values contained by the grid
containsKey &lt;key&gt; - indicates if the given key is contained by the grid
containsValue &lt;value&gt; - indicates if the given value is contained by the grid
map - returns a list of the key-value pairs in the grid

query &lt;query&gt; - executes a query on the grid

help - this info
exit - this node exists
client-1&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>For example to add new items to the grid one can use:</para>

      <programlisting>client-1&gt;<emphasis role="bold">put 1 unu</emphasis>
null
client-1&gt;<emphasis role="bold">put 1 one</emphasis>
old value = [unu]
client-1&gt;<emphasis role="bold">size</emphasis>
1
client-1&gt;<emphasis role="bold">put 2 two</emphasis>
null
client-1&gt;<emphasis role="bold">size</emphasis>
2
client-1&gt;</programlisting>

      <para>Multiple instances can be created at the same time. Once started,
      the new clients automatically see the existing region and its
      information. Start a second client with the command line
      '<literal>HelloWorld.exe client-2</literal>'</para>

      <programlisting>Hello World!
...

client-2&gt;<emphasis role="bold">size</emphasis>
2
client-2&gt;<emphasis role="bold">map</emphasis>
[2=two][1=one]
client-2&gt;
</programlisting>

      <para>Experiment with the example, start (and stop) as many instances as
      you want, run various commands in one instance and see how the others
      react. To preserve data, the Java Cache Servier needs to be running at
      all times.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
